<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../TAN-2018/schemas/TAN-T.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="../../TAN-2018/schemas/TAN-T.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://textalign.net/release/TAN-2018/schemas/TAN-T.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="http://textalign.net/release/TAN-2018/schemas/TAN-T.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<TAN-T xmlns="tag:textalign.net,2015:ns"
   id="tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-t:ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill:model-object-refs"
       TAN-version="2018">
   <head>
      <name>Categories, Aristotle, English translation by E. M. Edghill</name>
      <license which="by_4.0"/>
      <licensor who="kalvesmaki"/>
      <source>
         <IRI>http://id.lib.harvard.edu/aleph/007901738/catalog</IRI>
         <name>Aristotle: Categoriae &amp; De interpretatione by E.M. Edghill. Analytica priora / by
            A.J. Jenkinson. Analytica posteriora / by G.R.G. Mure. Oxford : Clarendon Press, 1926.
         </name>
      </source>
      <key>
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-key:aristotle</IRI>
         <name>General keywords associated with the Aristotle TAN collection</name>
         <location when-accessed="2018-01-19T11:15:34.508-05:00"
                   href="TAN-key/aristotle.TAN-key.xml"/>
      </key>
      <see-also relationship="model">
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-t:ar.cat.grc.1949.minio-paluello:object-refs</IRI>
         <name>Categories, Aristotle, Greek text by Minio-Paluello</name>
         <location href="ar.cat.grc.1949.minio-paluello.ref-scriptum-native.xml"
                   when-accessed="2018-03-08-05:00"/>
      </see-also>
      <see-also relationship="ade">
         <IRI>tag:kalvesmaki.com,2014:tan-t:ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill:semantic-refs</IRI>
         <name>Categories, Aristotle, English translation by E. M. Edghill</name>
         <location href="ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill.ref-logical-after-grc.xml"
                   when-accessed="2018-03-08-05:00"/>
      </see-also>
      <definitions>
         <algorithm xml:id="xslt1">
            <IRI>tag:textalign.net,2015:stylesheet:remodel-via-tan-t</IRI>
            <name>Stylesheet to create a TAN file.</name>
            <desc>Stylesheet at: ../../do%20things/remodel/remodel%20via%20TAN-T.xsl</desc>
         </algorithm>
         <div-type xml:id="p" which="page"/>
         <div-type which="column (page)" xml:id="c"/>
         <div-type which="line (physical)" xml:id="l"/>
         <work which="Aristotle, Categories"/>
         <person xml:id="kalvesmaki" which="Joel Kalvesmaki"/>
         <role xml:id="editor" which="editor"/>
         <role xml:id="stylesheet1" which="stylesheet"/>
         <relationship xml:id="ade" which="resegmented copy"/>
         <relationship which="model" xml:id="model"/>
         <relationship which="different work version" xml:id="alt"/>
         <relationship which="old version" xml:id="prev"/>
      </definitions>
      
      <alter>
         <normalization which="no hyphens"/>
      </alter>
      <resp who="xslt1" roles="stylesheet1"/>
      <resp roles="editor" who="kalvesmaki"/>
      <change when="2018-03-07" who="kalvesmaki" flags="error">Fixed major blunder in segmentation.
         9.1-3 to 8.7-9 and 9.4 and 9.6 are out; 9.5 to 9.1 and 9.7 to 9.2. 9.2[olim 7].3 to 10.1.1
         and renumber 10.1.1-2 by +1. </change>
      <change when="2018-01-19-05:00" who="kalvesmaki">Copied from official examples to begin new Aristotle collection.</change>
      <change when="2016-06-22T08:04:25.003-04:00" who="kalvesmaki">Reformatted according to first
         model found. Backup made at
         file:/C:/Users/jdkalv/Dropbox/TAN/library/TAN-2018/examples/ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill.ref-logical-201606220804250030400.xml.</change>
      <change when="2016-01-26-04:00" who="kalvesmaki">Started new file.</change>
      
      <change who="xslt1" when="2018-03-08T07:38:40.14-05:00">Input from file:/C:/Users/jdkalv/Dropbox/TAN/library-arithmeticus/aristotle/ar.cat.eng.1926.edghill.ref-logical-after-grc.xml proportionally remodeled after template at file:/C:/Users/jdkalv/Dropbox/TAN/library-arithmeticus/aristotle/ar.cat.grc.1949.minio-paluello.ref-scriptum-native.xml</change>
      </head>
   <body xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">Things are said to be named 'equivocally' when, though they have a common name, the </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">definition corresponding with the name differs for each. Thus, a real man and a figure in a picture </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">can both lay claim to the name 'animal'; yet these are equivocally so named, for, though they </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">have a common name, the definition corresponding with the name differs for each. For should </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">any one define in what sense each is an animal, his definition in the one </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">case will be appropriate to that case only. On the other hand, things are said </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">to be named 'univocally' which have both the name and the definition answering to the name </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">in common. A man and an ox are both 'animal', and these are univocally </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">so named, inasmuch as not only the name, but also the definition, is </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">the same in both cases: for if a man should state in what </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">sense each is an animal, the statement in the one case would be identical </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">with that in the other. Things are said to be named 'derivatively', which </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">derive their name from some other name, but differ from it in termination. </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">Thus the grammarian derives his name from the word 'grammar', and the </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">courageous man from the word 'courage'. </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">Forms of speech are either </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">simple or composite. Examples of the latter are such expressions </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">as 'the man runs', 'the man wins'; of the </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">former 'man', 'ox', 'runs', 'wins'. </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">Of things themselves some are predicable of a subject, </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">and are never present in a subject. Thus 'man' is </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">predicable of the individual man, and is never present in a subject. </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">By being 'present in a subject' I do not mean present as parts </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">are present in a whole, but being incapable of existence apart from the </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">said subject. Some things, again, are present in a subject, but are never predicable </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">of a subject. For instance, a certain point of grammatical knowledge is </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">present in the mind, but is not predicable of any subject; or again, a </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">certain whiteness may be present in the body (for colour requires a material </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">basis), yet it is never predicable of anything. Other things, again, are </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">both predicable of a subject and present in a subject. </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">Thus while knowledge is present in the human mind, it </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">is predicable of grammar. There is, lastly, a class of </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">things which are neither present in a subject </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">nor predicable of a subject, such as the individual </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">man or the individual horse. But, to speak more generally, that which is individual </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">and has the character of a unit is never predicable of a subject. Yet in some cases there is </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">nothing to prevent such being present in a subject. Thus a certain point of grammatical knowledge is </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">present in a subject. </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">When one thing is predicated of another, all </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">that which is predicable of the predicate will </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">be predicable also of the subject. Thus, 'man' is predicated </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">of the individual man; but 'animal' is predicated of 'man'; </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">it will, therefore, be predicable of the individual man </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">also: for the individual man is both 'man' and 'animal'. </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">If genera are different and co-ordinate, their differentiae are themselves different in </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">kind. Take as an instance the genus 'animal' and the genus 'knowledge'. </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">'With feet', 'two-footed', 'winged', 'aquatic', are differentiae of 'animal'; the </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">species of knowledge are not distinguished by the same differentiae. One </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">species of knowledge does not differ from another in being 'two-footed'. But where </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">one genus is subordinate to another, there is nothing to prevent their having the same differentiae: </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">for the greater class is predicated of the lesser, </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">so that all the differentiae of the predicate will be differentiae </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">also of the subject. </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">Expressions which are in no way </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">composite signify substance, quantity, quality, relation, place, time, </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">position, state, action, or affection. To sketch my meaning </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">roughly, examples of substance are 'man' or 'the horse', of quantity, such terms as 'two cubits long' </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">or 'three cubits long', of quality, such attributes as 'white', 'grammatical'. 'Double', 'half', </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">'greater', fall under the category of relation; 'in a the market place', 'in the Lyceum', under </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">that of place; 'yesterday', 'last year', under that of time. 'Lying', 'sitting', are terms </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">indicating position, 'shod', 'armed', state; 'to lance', </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">'to cauterize', action; 'to be lanced', 'to be cauterized', affection. </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">No one of these terms, in and by itself, involves an </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">affirmation; it is by the combination of such terms that </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">positive or negative statements arise. For every assertion must, as is </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">admitted, be either true or false, whereas expressions which </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">are not in any way composite such as 'man', 'white', </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">'runs', 'wins', cannot be either true or false. </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">Substance, in the truest and primary and most definite </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">sense of the word, is that which is neither predicable of </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">a subject nor present in a subject; for instance, the individual man </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">or horse. But in a secondary sense those things are called substances within </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">which, as species, the primary substances are included; also those which, </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">as genera, include the species. For instance, the individual man is included in </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">the species 'man', and the genus to which the species belongs is 'animal'; </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">these, therefore-that is to say, the species 'man' and the genus 'animal,-are termed </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">secondary substances. It is plain from what has been said </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">that both the name and the definition of the predicate </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">must be predicable of the subject. For instance, 'man' is predicted </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">of the individual man. Now in this case the name of the species </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">man' is applied to the individual, for we use the term 'man' in describing </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">the individual; and the definition of 'man' will also be predicated </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">of the individual man, for the individual man is both man </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">and animal. Thus, both the name and the definition of </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">the species are predicable of the individual. With regard, on the other hand, to those things </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">which are present in a subject, it is generally the case that neither their name nor their definition </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">is predicable of that in which they are present. Though, however, the definition is never </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">predicable, there is nothing in certain cases to prevent the name </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">being used. For instance, 'white' being present in a body is predicated </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">of that in which it is present, for a body is called </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">white: the definition, however, of the colour white' is never predicable of </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">the body. Everything except primary substances is either predicable </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">of a primary substance or present in a primary substance. This </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">becomes evident by reference to particular instances which occur. 'Animal' </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">is predicated of the species 'man', therefore of the individual man, for if there </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">were no individual man of whom it could be predicated, it could </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">not be predicated of the species 'man' at all. Again, colour is </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">present in body, therefore in individual bodies, for if there were </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">no individual body in which it was present, it could not be present in body at all. Thus </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">everything except primary substances is either predicated of </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">primary substances, or is present in them, and if these </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">last did not exist, it would be impossible for anything else to exist. </div>
            <!--<div n="6a" type="l"/>-->
            <!--<div n="6b" type="l"/>-->
            <!--<div n="6c" type="l"/>-->
            <div n="7" type="l">Of secondary substances, the species is more truly substance than </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">the genus, being more nearly related to primary substance. For if any </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">one should render an account of what a primary substance is, he would render a more instructive account, </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">and one more proper to the subject, by stating the species than by stating the genus. </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">Thus, he would give a more instructive account of an individual man by stating that he was man </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">than by stating that he was animal, for the former description is peculiar to the individual in </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">a greater degree, while the latter is too general. Again, the man who gives an account of the nature of an </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">individual tree will give a more instructive account by mentioning the species 'tree' than by mentioning the genus 'plant'. </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">Moreover, primary substances are most properly called substances in virtue of </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">the fact that they are the entities which underlie everything else, and </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">that everything else is either predicated of them or present in them. Now </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">the same relation which subsists between primary substance and everything else subsists </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">also between the species and the genus: for the species is to the genus as </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">subject is to predicate, since the genus is predicated of the species, </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">whereas the species cannot be predicated of the genus. Thus we have a </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">second ground for asserting that the species is more truly substance than the genus. Of species themselves, except </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">in the case of such as are genera, no one is more truly substance </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">than another. We should not give a more appropriate account of the individual man by stating </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">the species to which he belonged, than we should of an individual horse by adopting the </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">same method of definition. In the same way, of primary substances, no one </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">is more truly substance than another; an individual man is not more </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">truly substance than an individual ox. </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">It is, then, with good reason that of all that remains, when we </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">exclude primary substances, we concede to species and genera alone the name 'secondary substance', for these </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">alone of all the predicates convey a knowledge of primary substance. For </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">it is by stating the species or the genus that we appropriately define </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">any individual man; and we shall make our definition more exact by stating the </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">former than by stating the latter. All other things that </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">we state, such as that he is white, that he runs, </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">and so on, are irrelevant to the definition. Thus it is just that </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">these alone, apart from primary substances, should be called substances. Further, primary substances are </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">most properly so called, because they underlie and are the subjects </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">of everything else. Now the same relation that subsists between primary substance and everything else subsists also between </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">the species and the genus to which the primary substance belongs, on the one hand, and every attribute which </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">is not included within these, on the other. For these are the subjects </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">of all such. If we call an individual man 'skilled in grammar', the predicate </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">is applicable also to the species and to the genus to which he belongs. </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">This law holds good in all cases. </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">It is a common characteristic of all substance that it is never present </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">in a subject. For primary substance is neither present in a </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">subject nor predicated of a subject; while, with regard to secondary substances, it </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">is clear from the following arguments (apart from others) that they are not present in a subject. For </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">'man' is predicated of the individual man, but is not </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">present in any subject: for manhood is not present in </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">the individual man. In the same way, 'animal' is </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">also predicated of the individual man, but is not </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">present in him. Again, when a thing is present in a subject, </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">though the name may quite well be applied to that in which it is </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">present, the definition cannot be applied. Yet of secondary substances, not only the </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">name, but also the definition, applies to the subject: we should use </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">both the definition of the species and that of the genus </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">with reference to the individual man. Thus substance cannot be </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">present in a subject. Yet this is not peculiar to substance, for </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">it is also the case that differentiae cannot be present in subjects. The </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">characteristics 'terrestrial' and 'two-footed' are predicated of the </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">species 'man', but not present in it. For </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">they are not in man. Moreover, the definition of the differentia may </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">be predicated of that of which the differentia itself is predicated. For instance, </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">if the characteristic 'terrestrial' is predicated of the species 'man', the definition also of </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">that characteristic may be used to form the predicate of the species 'man': for 'man' is terrestrial. </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">The fact that the parts of substances appear to be present in the </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">whole, as in a subject, should not make us apprehensive lest we should have to </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">admit that such parts are not substances: for in explaining the phrase 'being present in a </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">subject', we stated' that we meant 'otherwise than as parts in a whole'. </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">It is the mark of substances and of differentiae that, in all propositions of </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">which they form the predicate, they are predicated univocally. For all such </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">propositions have for their subject either the individual or </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">the species. It is true that, inasmuch as primary substance is not </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">predicable of anything, it can never form the predicate of any proposition. But </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">of secondary substances, the species is predicated of the </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">individual, the genus both of the species and of the individual. </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">Similarly the differentiae are predicated of the species </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">and of the individuals. Moreover, the definition of the species </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">and that of the genus are applicable to the primary substance, and that </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">of the genus to the species. For all that is predicated of </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">the predicate will be predicated also of the subject. Similarly, the </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">definition of the differentiae will be applicable to the species and </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">to the individuals. But it was stated above that the word 'univocal' was applied to those things </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">which had both name and definition in common. It is, therefore, established that in every proposition, of which either </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">substance or a differentia forms the predicate, these are predicated univocally. </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">All substance appears to signify that which is individual. In </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">the case of primary substance this </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">is indisputably true, for the thing is </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">a unit. In the case of secondary substances, when we speak, for instance, of </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">'man' or 'animal', our form of speech gives the impression that we are here also </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">indicating that which is individual, but the impression is not strictly true; for a secondary </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">substance is not an individual, but a class with a certain qualification; for it is not one and </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">single as a primary substance is; the words 'man', 'animal', are predicable of more than </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">one subject. Yet species and genus do not merely indicate quality, like the term 'white'; </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">'white' indicates quality and nothing further, but species and </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">genus determine the quality with reference to a substance: </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">they signify substance qualitatively differentiated. The determinate qualification covers a larger field in the case </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">of the genus that in that of the species: he who uses the word 'animal' is herein using a word </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">of wider extension than he who uses the word 'man'. </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">Another mark of substance is that it has </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">no contrary. What could be the contrary of any primary substance, such as the individual man or animal? It </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">has none. Nor can the species or the </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">genus have a contrary. Yet this characteristic is not peculiar to substance, but </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">is true of many other things, such as quantity. There is nothing that forms the contrary </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">of 'two cubits long' or of 'three cubits long', or of 'ten', or of any such </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">term. A man may contend that 'much' is the contrary of 'little', or 'great' of 'small', </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">but of definite quantitative terms no contrary exists. </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">Substance, again, does not appear to admit of variation </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">of degree. I do not mean by this that one substance cannot be more or </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">less truly substance than another, for it has already been stated' that this </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">is the case; but that no single substance admits of varying degrees within itself. </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">For instance, one particular substance, 'man', cannot be more or less </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">man either than himself at some other time or than some </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">other man. One man cannot be more man than another, as that which is white may be more </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">or less white than some other white object, or as that which is beautiful may be </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">more or less beautiful than some other beautiful object. The same quality, moreover, is said to subsist </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">in a thing in varying degrees at different times. A body, being white, is said </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">to be whiter at one time than it was before, or, being warm, is said to </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">be warmer or less warm than at some other time. But substance is not said to </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">be more or less that which it is: a man is not more truly a man at </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">one time than he was before, nor is anything, if it is substance, more or less what </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">it is. Substance, then, does not admit of variation </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">of degree. </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">The most distinctive mark of substance appears to be that, while remaining numerically </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">one and the same, it is capable of admitting contrary qualities. From among </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">things other than substance, we should find ourselves </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">unable to bring forward any which possessed this mark. </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">Thus, one and the same colour cannot be </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">white and black. Nor can the same one action </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">be good and bad: this law holds good with </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">everything that is not substance. But one and the selfsame </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">substance, while retaining its identity, is yet capable of admitting contrary qualities. The same </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">individual person is at one time white, at another black, at </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">one time warm, at another cold, at one time good, </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">at another bad. This capacity is found nowhere else, though </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">it might be maintained that a statement or opinion was </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">an exception to the rule. The same statement, it is agreed, </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">can be both true and false. For if the statement 'he is sitting' is </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">true, yet, when the person in question has risen, the same statement </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">will be false. The same applies to opinions. For if any one </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">thinks truly that a person is sitting, yet, when that person has risen, this </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">same opinion, if still held, will be false. Yet although this exception may be allowed, </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">there is, nevertheless, a difference in the manner in which the thing takes place. It is by </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">themselves changing that substances admit contrary qualities. It is thus that that which was hot </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">becomes cold, for it has entered into a different state. Similarly that which </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">was white becomes black, and that which was bad good, by a process </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">of change; and in the same way in all other cases it is </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">by changing that substances are capable of admitting contrary qualities. But statements and opinions </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">themselves remain unaltered in all respects: it is by the alteration in </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">the facts of the case that the contrary quality comes to be theirs. The </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">statement 'he is sitting' remains unaltered, but it is </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">at one time true, at another false, according to circumstances. </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">What has been said of statements applies also to opinions. Thus, in respect of the manner in </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">which the thing takes place, it is the peculiar mark of substance that it should be capable </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">of admitting contrary qualities; for it is by itself changing that it does so. If, then, a man </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">should make this exception and contend that statements and opinions are capable of admitting contrary qualities, his </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">contention is unsound. For statements and opinions are said to have </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">this capacity, not because they themselves undergo modification, but because this modification </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">occurs in the case of something else. The truth or falsity </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">of a statement depends on facts, and not on any power on </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">the part of the statement itself of admitting contrary qualities. In short, </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">there is nothing which can alter the nature of statements and opinions. As, then, no </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">change takes place in themselves, these cannot be said to be capable of admitting </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">contrary qualities. But it is by reason of the modification which takes place within the substance itself that a </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">substance is said to be capable of admitting contrary qualities; for a substance admits </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">within itself either disease or health, whiteness or blackness. It is in </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">this sense that it is said to be capable of admitting contrary qualities. </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">To sum up, it is a distinctive mark of substance, that, while remaining numerically one and the same, it is capable of admitting contrary qualities, </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">the modification taking place through a change in the substance itself. Let these remarks suffice on the subject </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">of substance. </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">Quantity is either discrete or continuous. </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">Moreover, some quantities are such that each part of the whole has a relative position to </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">the other parts: others have within them no such relation of part to part. Instances </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">of discrete quantities are number and speech; of continuous, </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">lines, surfaces, solids, and, besides these, time and </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">place. In the case of the parts of a number, there </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">is no common boundary at which they join. For example: </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">two fives make ten, but the two fives have </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">no common boundary, but are separate; the parts three </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">and seven also do not join at any boundary. Nor, to generalize, would </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">it ever be possible in the case of number that there should be a common boundary among the </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">parts; they are always separate. Number, therefore, is a discrete quantity. </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">The same is true of speech. That </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">speech is a quantity is evident: for it is measured in </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">long and short syllables. I mean here that speech </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">which is vocal. Moreover, it is a discrete quantity for its parts </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">have no common boundary. There is no common boundary at which the </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">syllables join, but each is separate and distinct from the rest. </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">A line, on the other hand, is a continuous quantity, for it is possible to </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">find a common boundary at which its parts join. In the case of </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">the line, this common boundary is the point; in the case of the plane, it is the line: for the </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">parts of the plane have also a common boundary. Similarly you can find a common </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">boundary in the case of the parts of a solid, </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">namely either a line or a plane. Space and time also </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">belong to this class of quantities. Time, past, present, and </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">future, forms a continuous whole. Space, likewise, is </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">a continuous quantity; for the parts of a solid occupy </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">a certain space, and these have a common boundary; it follows that </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">the parts of space also, which are occupied by the parts of </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">the solid, have the same common boundary as the parts </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">of the solid. Thus, not only time, but space also, is a continuous quantity, for </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">its parts have a common boundary. </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">Quantities consist either of parts which bear a </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">relative position each to each, or of parts which do not. </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">The parts of a line bear a relative position to each other, for </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">each lies somewhere, and it would be possible to distinguish each, and to state </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">the position of each on the plane and to explain to what </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">sort of part among the rest each was contiguous. Similarly the parts of </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">a plane have position, for it could similarly be stated what </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">was the position of each and what sort of parts were contiguous. </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">The same is true with regard to the solid and to space. But </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">it would be impossible to show that the parts of a </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">number had a relative position each to each, or a particular </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">position, or to state what parts were contiguous. Nor could this be done in the case of time, </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">for none of the parts of time has an abiding existence, and </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">that which does not abide can hardly have position. It would </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">be better to say that such parts had a relative order, in virtue </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">of one being prior to another. Similarly with number: in counting, </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">'one' is prior to 'two', and 'two' to 'three', </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">and thus the parts of number may be said to possess a relative order, though it would be impossible to discover any distinct position </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">for each. This holds good also in the case of speech. None of its parts has </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">an abiding existence: when once a syllable is pronounced, it is not </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">possible to retain it, so that, naturally, as the parts do not abide, they </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">cannot have position. Thus, some quantities consist of parts which have </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">position, and some of those which have not. </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">Strictly speaking, only the things which I have mentioned belong to the category of quantity: everything </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">else that is called quantitative is a quantity in a secondary sense. It is because we </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">have in mind some one of these quantities, properly so called, that we apply quantitative terms to </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">other things. We speak of what is white as large, because the surface over which the white extends is </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">large; we speak of an action or a process as lengthy, because the time covered is long; these </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">things cannot in their own right claim the quantitative epithet. For instance, should any one </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">explain how long an action was, his statement would be made in terms of the time </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">taken, to the effect that it lasted a year, or something of that sort. In the </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">same way, he would explain the size of a white object in terms of surface, for he </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">would state the area which it covered. Thus the things already mentioned, and these alone, </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">are in their intrinsic nature quantities; nothing else can claim the name in its own right, but, </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">if at all, only in a secondary sense. </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">Quantities have no contraries. In the case of definite quantities this </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">is obvious; thus, there is nothing that is the contrary of </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">'two cubits long' or of 'three cubits long', or of a surface, </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">or of any such quantities. A man might, indeed, argue that </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">'much' was the contrary of 'little', and 'great' of 'small'. But </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">these are not quantitative, but relative; things are not great or </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">small absolutely, they are so called rather as the result of an </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">act of comparison. For instance, a mountain is called small, a grain large, </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">in virtue of the fact that the latter is greater than others of </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">its kind, the former less. Thus there is a reference here to an external </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">standard, for if the terms 'great' and 'small' were used absolutely, a </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">mountain would never be called small or a grain large. Again, we say that </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">there are many people in a village, and few in Athens, although those in the city </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">are many times as numerous as those in the village: or we say that a house has many </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">in it, and a theatre few, though those in the theatre far outnumber those in the house. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">The terms 'two cubits long, "three cubits long,' </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">and so on indicate quantity, the terms 'great' </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">and 'small' indicate relation, for they have reference to </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">an external standard. It is, therefore, plain that these are to be classed as relative. </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">Again, whether we define them as quantitative or </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">not, they have no contraries: for how can there be a contrary of </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">an attribute which is not to be apprehended in or by itself, but only </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">by reference to something external? Again, if 'great' and 'small' are contraries, it will come </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">about that the same subject can admit contrary qualities at one and the same time, </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">and that things will themselves be contrary to themselves. For it happens at times </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">that the same thing is both small and great. For the same thing may be </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">small in comparison with one thing, and great in comparison with another, so that </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">the same thing comes to be both small and </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">great at one and the same time, and is of such a nature </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="6" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">as to admit contrary qualities at one and the same moment. Yet it was agreed, when substance was being discussed, </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">that nothing admits contrary qualities at one and the same moment. For though substance is capable of admitting contrary qualities, yet no </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">one is at the same time both sick and healthy, nothing is at the same time both white and </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">black. Nor is there anything which is qualified in contrary ways at one and the same time. Moreover, </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">if these were contraries, they would themselves be contrary to themselves. For if 'great' is </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">the contrary of 'small', and the same thing is both great and small at the </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">same time, then 'small' or 'great' is the contrary of itself. But </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">this is impossible. The term 'great', therefore, is </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">not the contrary of the term 'small', nor 'much' of 'little'. And </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">even though a man should call these terms not relative but quantitative, they </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">would not have contraries. It is in the case of space that quantity most plausibly </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">appears to admit of a contrary. For men define the term 'above' as the contrary of 'below', when </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">it is the region at the centre they mean by 'below'; and this is so, because </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">nothing is farther from the extremities of the universe than the region at the centre. Indeed, it </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">seems that in defining contraries of every kind men have recourse to a spatial metaphor, </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">for they say that those things are contraries which, within the same class, </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">are separated by the greatest possible distance. </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">Quantity does not, it appears, admit of variation of degree. </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">One thing cannot be two cubits long in a greater degree </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">than another. Similarly with regard to number: what is 'three' is not more truly three than what </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">is 'five' is five; nor is one set of three more truly three than another set. Again, one </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">period of time is not said to be more truly time than another. Nor is there any </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">other kind of quantity, of all that have been mentioned, with regard to which variation of degree can be predicated. The </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">category of quantity, therefore, does not admit of variation of degree. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">The most distinctive mark of quantity is that equality and inequality are predicated </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">of it. Each of the aforesaid quantities is said to be </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">equal or unequal. For instance, one solid is said to be </div>
            <div n="28a" type="l">equal or unequal to another; number, too, and time can </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">have these terms applied to them, indeed can all those </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">kinds of quantity that have been mentioned. </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">That which is not a quantity can by no means, it would seem, </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">be termed equal or unequal to anything else. One particular disposition or one </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">particular quality, such as whiteness, is by no means compared with another in terms of </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">equality and inequality but rather in terms of similarity. Thus it is the distinctive </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">mark of quantity that it can be called equal and unequal. </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">Those things are called relative, which, being either said to be of something </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">else or related to something else, are explained by reference to that other thing. For </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">instance, the word 'superior' is explained by reference to something else, for it is superiority </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">over something else that is meant. Similarly, the expression 'double' has this external reference, for </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">it is the double of something else that is meant. So it is with everything else </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">of this kind. There are, moreover, other relatives, e.g. habit, </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">disposition, perception, knowledge, and attitude. The significance of all these </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">is explained by a reference to something else and in no other way. </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">Thus, a habit is a habit of something, knowledge is knowledge of something, attitude is the </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">attitude of something. So it is with all other relatives that have been mentioned. Those terms, </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">then, are called relative, the nature of which is explained by reference to something else, the preposition 'of' or </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">some other preposition being used to indicate the relation. Thus, one mountain is called great in comparison with </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">son with another; for the mountain claims this attribute by comparison with something. Again, that which is </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">called similar must be similar to something else, and all other such attributes have this </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">external reference. It is to be noted that lying and standing and sitting </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">are particular attitudes, but attitude is itself a relative term. To lie, to </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">stand, to be seated, are not themselves attitudes, but </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">take their name from the aforesaid attitudes. </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">It is possible for relatives to have contraries. Thus </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">virtue has a contrary, vice, these both being relatives; knowledge, too, has </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">a contrary, ignorance. But this is not the mark of all relatives; </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">'double' and 'triple' have no contrary, nor </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">indeed has any such term. It also appears </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">that relatives can admit of variation of degree. For 'like' </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">and 'unlike', 'equal' and 'unequal', have the modifications 'more' and 'less' applied to </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">them, and each of these is relative in character: for the terms </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">'like' and 'unequal' bear a reference to something external. Yet, again, </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">it is not every relative term that admits of variation of degree. No </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">term such as 'double' admits of </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">this modification. </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">All relatives have correlatives: by the term 'slave' we mean the </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">slave of a master, by the term 'master', the master of </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">a slave; by 'double', the double of its hall; by 'half', the </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">half of its double; by 'greater', greater than that which is less; by </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">'less,' less than that which is greater. So it is with every other </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">relative term; but the case we use to express the correlation differs in some </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">instances. Thus, by knowledge we mean knowledge the knowable; by the knowable, that </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">which is to be apprehended by knowledge; by perception, perception of the perceptible; by </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">the perceptible, that which is apprehended by perception. Sometimes, however, reciprocity of correlation does not </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">appear to exist. This comes about when a blunder is made, and that to which </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">the relative is related is not accurately stated. If a man states that a wing is necessarily </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">relative to a bird, the connexion between these two will not be reciprocal, for it will not be possible </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="7" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">to say that a bird is a bird by reason of its wings. The reason is that the original statement was inaccurate, for the </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">wing is not said to be relative to the bird qua bird, since many creatures besides birds have wings, but qua winged creature. </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">If, then, the </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">statement is made accurate, the connexion will be reciprocal, for we can speak of a wing, having reference necessarily to a </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">winged creature, and of a winged creature as being such because of its wings. Occasionally, perhaps, it </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">is necessary to coin words, if no word exists by which a </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">correlation can adequately be explained. If we define a rudder as necessarily having </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">reference to a boat, our definition will not be appropriate, for the rudder </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">does not have this reference to a boat qua boat, as there are boats which </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">have no rudders. Thus we cannot use the terms reciprocally, for the word 'boat' cannot be said </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">to find its explanation in the word 'rudder'. As there is no existing word, </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">our definition would perhaps be more accurate if we coined </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">some word like 'ruddered' as the correlative of 'rudder'. If we express </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">ourselves thus accurately, at any rate the terms are reciprocally connected, for the 'ruddered' thing is </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">'ruddered' in virtue of its rudder. So it is in all other cases. A </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">head will be more accurately defined as the correlative of that which is 'headed', than as </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">that of an animal, for the animal does not have a head qua animal, since </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">many animals have no head. Thus we may perhaps most easily comprehend </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">that to which a thing is related, when a name does not exist, if, from </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">that which has a name, we derive a new name, and apply it to </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">that with which the first is reciprocally connected, as in the aforesaid instances, when we derived </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">the word 'winged' from 'wing' and from 'rudder'. All relatives, </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">then, if properly defined, have a correlative. I </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">add this condition because, if that to which they are related is stated as haphazard and not </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">accurately, the two are not found to be interdependent. Let me state what I mean more </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">clearly. Even in the case of acknowledged correlatives, and where names exist for each, there </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">will be no interdependence if one of the two is denoted, not by that name </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">which expresses the correlative notion, but by one of irrelevant significance. The term 'slave,' </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">if defined as related, not to a master, but to a </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">man, or a biped, or anything of that sort, not reciprocally connected with that in relation to which </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">it is defined, for the statement is not exact. Further, if one thing is said to be correlative with another, </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">and the terminology used is correct, then, though all irrelevant attributes should be </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">removed, and only that one attribute left in virtue of which it was correctly stated </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">to be correlative with that other, the stated correlation will still exist. If the </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">correlative of 'the slave' is said to be 'the master', then, </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">though all irrelevant attributes of the said 'master', such as 'biped', </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">'receptive of knowledge', 'human', should be removed, and the attribute 'master' </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">alone left, the stated correlation existing between him and the </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">slave will remain the same, for it is of a master that a slave is said to </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">be the slave. On the other hand, if, of two correlatives, one is not correctly termed, </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">then, when all other attributes are removed and that alone is left in virtue of which </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">it was stated to be correlative, the stated correlation will be found to have disappeared. </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">For suppose the correlative of 'the slave' should be said to be 'the man', or the </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">correlative of 'the wing' 'the bird'; if the attribute 'master' be withdrawn from' the man', </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">the correlation between 'the man' and 'the slave' will cease to exist, for if the man is </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">not a master, the slave is not a slave. Similarly, if the attribute 'winged' </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">be withdrawn from 'the bird', 'the wing' will no longer </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">be relative; for if the so-called correlative is not winged, it follows that 'the wing' has no correlative. </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">Thus it is essential that the correlated terms should be exactly designated; </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">if there is a name existing, the statement will be easy; if </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">not, it is doubtless our duty to construct names. When the </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">terminology is thus correct, it is evident that all correlatives </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">are interdependent. </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">Correlatives are thought to come into existence simultaneously. This is for the most </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">part true, as in the case of the double and the half. The existence of the half necessitates the existence of </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">that of which it is a half. Similarly the existence of a master necessitates the existence of a slave, </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">and that of a slave implies that of a master; these are merely instances of a </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">general rule. Moreover, they cancel one another; for if </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">there is no double it follows that there </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">is no half, and vice versa; this rule also applies to </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">all such correlatives. Yet it does not appear to be true in all cases </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">that correlatives come into existence simultaneously. The object of knowledge would </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">appear to exist before knowledge itself, for it is usually </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">the case that we acquire knowledge of objects already existing; it </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">would be difficult, if not impossible, to find a branch of knowledge the beginning of the existence of </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">which was contemporaneous with that of its object. Again, while the object of knowledge, if it ceases </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">to exist, cancels at the same time the knowledge which was its correlative, the converse of this </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">is not true. It is true that if the object of knowledge does not exist there can be no knowledge: </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">for there will no longer be anything to know. Yet it is equally true that, if knowledge of a certain object does </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">not exist, the object may nevertheless quite well exist. Thus, in the case of the squaring of the </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">circle, if indeed that process is an object of knowledge, though it itself exists as an object of </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">knowledge, yet the knowledge of it has not yet come into existence. Again, if all animals ceased </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">to exist, there would be no knowledge, but there might yet be many objects </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">of knowledge. This is likewise the case with regard to perception: </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">for the object of perception is, it appears, prior to the act of perception. </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">If the perceptible is annihilated, perception also will cease to exist; but the annihilation of </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">perception does not cancel the existence of the perceptible. For perception implies a body perceived </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">and a body in which perception takes place. Now if that which is perceptible is </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="8" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">annihilated, it follows that the body is annihilated, for the body is a perceptible thing; </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">and if the body does not exist, it follows that perception also ceases to exist. </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">Thus the annihilation of the perceptible involves that of perception. But the annihilation of perception does not </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">involve that of the perceptible. For if the animal is annihilated, it </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">follows that perception also is annihilated, but perceptibles such as </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">body, heat, sweetness, bitterness, and so on, will remain. Again, perception </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">is generated at the same time as the perceiving subject, for it </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">comes into existence at the same time as the animal. But the </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">perceptible surely exists before perception; for fire and water and such elements, </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">out of which the animal is itself composed, exist before the animal </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">is an animal at all, and before perception. Thus it would seem that the </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">perceptible exists before perception. </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">It may be questioned whether it is true that no substance is relative, </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">as seems to be the case, or whether exception is to be made in </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">the case of certain secondary substances. With regard to primary substances, it is quite true that there </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">is no such possibility, for neither wholes nor parts of primary substances are relative. </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">The individual man or ox is not defined </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">with reference to something external. Similarly with the parts: </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">a particular hand or head is not defined as a particular hand or </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">head of a particular person, but as the hand or head </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">of a particular person. It is true also, for the most part at least, </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">in the case of secondary substances; the species 'man' and the species 'ox' are not defined with </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">reference to anything outside themselves. Wood, again, is only relative in so far as it is some one's </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">property, not in so far as it is wood. It is plain, then, that in </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">the cases mentioned substance is not relative. But with regard to some secondary </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">substances there is a difference of opinion; thus, such terms as 'head' and 'hand' </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">are defined with reference to that of which the things indicated are a </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">part, and so it comes about that these appear to have a relative character. </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">Indeed, if our definition of that which is relative was complete, </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">it is very difficult, if not impossible, to prove that </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">no substance is relative. If, however, our definition was not complete, if those things only are properly </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">called relative in the case of which relation to an external object is a necessary condition of existence, perhaps </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">some explanation of the dilemma may be found. The former definition does indeed apply to </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">all relatives, but the fact that a thing is explained with </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">reference to something else does not make it essentially relative. From </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">this it is plain that, if a man definitely apprehends a relative thing, he </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">will also definitely apprehend that to which it is relative. </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">Indeed this is self-evident: for if a man knows that some particular </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">thing is relative, assuming that we call that a relative in the case of which relation to </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">something is a necessary condition of existence, he knows that also to which it is related. </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">For if he does not know at all that to which it is related, he will </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">not know whether or not it is relative. This is clear, moreover, </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">in particular instances. If a man knows definitely that such and such a thing </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">is 'double', he will also forthwith know definitely that of which it is the double. </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">For if there is nothing definite of which he knows it to be the </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">double, he does not know at all that it is double. Again, if he knows </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">that a thing is more beautiful, it follows necessarily that he will forthwith </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">definitely know that also than which it is more beautiful. He will not merely </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">know indefinitely that it is more beautiful than something which is less beautiful, for </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">this would be supposition, not knowledge. For if he does </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">not know definitely that than which it is more beautiful, can no longer claim to know definitely that it is more beautiful </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">than something else which is less beautiful: for it might be that nothing was less beautiful. It is, therefore, evident that if a </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">man apprehends some relative thing definitely, he necessarily knows that also </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">definitely to which it is related. Now the head, the hand, and </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">such things are substances, and it is possible to know their essential character </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">definitely, but it does not necessarily follow that we should know that to which </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">they are related. It is not possible to know forthwith whose </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">head or hand is meant. Thus these are not relatives, </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">and, this being the case, it would be true to say </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">that no substance is relative in character. It is perhaps a </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">difficult matter, in such cases, to make a positive statement without </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">more exhaustive examination, but to have raised questions with regard to details </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">is not without advantage. </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">By 'quality' I mean that in virtue of which people are said to be such and such. Quality </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">is a term that is used in many senses. One </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">sort of quality let us call 'habit' or 'disposition'. Habit differs </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">from disposition in being more lasting and more firmly established. </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">The various kinds of knowledge and of virtue are habits, for knowledge, </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">even when acquired only in a moderate degree, is, it is agreed, </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">abiding in its character and difficult to displace, unless some great </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">mental upheaval takes place, through disease or any such cause. </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">The virtues, also, such as justice, self-restraint, and so on, </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">are not easily dislodged or dismissed, so as to give </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">place to vice. By a disposition, on the other hand, we mean a condition </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">that is easily changed and quickly gives place to its opposite. Thus, heat, </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">cold, disease, health, and so on are dispositions. For a man </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">is disposed in one way or another with reference to </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">these, but quickly changes, becoming cold instead of warm, ill instead </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="9" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">of well. So it is with all other dispositions also, unless through </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">lapse of time a disposition has itself become inveterate and almost impossible </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">to dislodge: in which case we should perhaps go so far as </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">to call it a habit. It is evident that men incline to call those conditions </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">habits which are of a more or less permanent type and difficult to displace; for those </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">who are not retentive of knowledge, but volatile, are not said to have </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">such and such a 'habit' as regards knowledge, yet they are disposed, we </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">may say, either better or worse, towards knowledge. Thus habit differs from disposition in </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">this, that while the latter in ephemeral, the former is permanent </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">and difficult to alter. Habits are at the same time dispositions, </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">but dispositions are not necessarily habits. For those who have some specific habit may be </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">said also, in virtue of that habit, to be thus or thus disposed; but those who are disposed in some </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">specific way have not in all cases the corresponding habit. </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">Another sort of quality is that in virtue of which, for example, </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">we call men good boxers or runners, or healthy or sickly: in fact it </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">includes all those terms which refer to inborn capacity or incapacity. Such things </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">are not predicated of a person in virtue of his disposition, but in virtue </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">of his inborn capacity or incapacity to do something with ease or to </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">avoid defeat of any kind. Persons are called good boxers or good runners, </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">not in virtue of such and such a disposition, but in virtue </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">of an inborn capacity to accomplish something with ease. Men are called healthy </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">in virtue of the inborn capacity of easy resistance to those unhealthy </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">influences that may ordinarily arise; unhealthy, in virtue of the lack </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">of this capacity. Similarly with regard to softness </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">and hardness. Hardness is predicated of a thing because it has that capacity of </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">resistance which enables it to withstand disintegration; softness, again, is predicated of a thing by </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">reason of the lack of that capacity. </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">A third class within this category is that of affective qualities </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">and affections. Sweetness, bitterness, sourness, are examples of this sort of </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">quality, together with all that is akin to these; heat, moreover, </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">and cold, whiteness, and blackness are affective qualities. It is </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">evident that these are qualities, for those things that possess them are themselves said </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">to be such and such by reason of their presence. Honey is called sweet because </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">it contains sweetness; the body is called white because it </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">contains whiteness; and so in all other cases. The term </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">'affective quality' is not used as indicating that those things which admit these </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">qualities are affected in any way. Honey is not called sweet because it is affected </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">in a specific way, nor is this what is meant in any other instance. Similarly </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">heat and cold are called affective qualities, not </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">because those things which admit them are </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">affected. What is meant is that these said qualities </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">are capable of producing an 'affection' in the </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">way of perception. For sweetness has the power of affecting the sense of </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">taste; heat, that of touch; and so it is with the rest </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">of these qualities. Whiteness and blackness, however, and the other colours, </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">are not said to be affective qualities in this sense, but </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">-because they themselves are the results of an affection. It </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">is plain that many changes of colour take place because of </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">affections. When a man is ashamed, he blushes; when he is </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">afraid, he becomes pale, and so on. So true is this, that when a man </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">is by nature liable to such affections, arising from some concomitance of elements in his constitution, it is a </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">probable inference that he has the corresponding complexion of skin. For the same disposition of bodily elements, </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">which in the former instance was momentarily present in the case of an access </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">of shame, might be a result of a man's natural temperament, so as to produce </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">the corresponding colouring also as a natural characteristic. All conditions, therefore, </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">of this kind, if caused by certain permanent </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">and lasting affections, are called affective qualities. For </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">pallor and duskiness of complexion are called qualities, inasmuch as </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">we are said to be such and such in virtue of </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">them, not only if they originate in natural constitution, but also if </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">they come about through long disease or sunburn, and are difficult </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">to remove, or indeed remain throughout life. For in the same </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">way we are said to be such and such because of these. </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">Those conditions, however, which arise from causes which may easily be rendered ineffective or speedily </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">removed, are called, not qualities, but affections: for we are not said to be </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">such virtue of them. The man who blushes through shame is not said to be </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">a constitutional blusher, nor is the man who becomes pale through fear said to </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">be constitutionally pale. He is said rather to have been affected. Thus such </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">conditions are called affections, not qualities. In like manner </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">there are affective qualities and affections of </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">the soul. That temper with which a man is born and which </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">has its origin in certain deep-seated affections is called a quality. I </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="10" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">mean such conditions as insanity, irascibility, and so on: for people are said </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">to be mad or irascible in virtue of these. Similarly those abnormal </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">psychic states which are not inborn, but arise from the concomitance </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">of certain other elements, and are difficult to remove, or </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">altogether permanent, are called qualities, for in virtue of them men are said to be such and such. </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">Those, however, which arise from causes easily rendered ineffective are called affections, </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">not qualities. Suppose that a man is irritable when vexed: he is not even </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">spoken of as a bad-tempered man, when in such circumstances he loses his temper somewhat, but </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">rather is said to be affected. Such conditions are therefore termed, not </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">qualities, but affections. </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">The fourth sort of quality is figure and the </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">shape that belongs to a thing; and besides this, straightness </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">and curvedness and any other qualities of this type; each of </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">these defines a thing as being such and such. Because it is triangular or </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">quadrangular a thing is said to have a specific character, or again because it is straight or curved; </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">in fact a thing's shape in every case gives rise to a qualification of it. Rarity </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">and density, roughness and smoothness, seem to be terms </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">indicating quality: yet these, it would appear, really belong to </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">a class different from that of quality. For it is rather a certain relative position of </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">the parts composing the thing thus qualified which, it appears, is indicated by each of these terms. A thing is dense, owing </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">to the fact that its parts are closely combined with one another; rare, because there are </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">interstices between the parts; smooth, because its parts lie, so </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">to speak, evenly; rough, because some parts project beyond others. </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">There may be other sorts of quality, but those that are most </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">properly so called have, we may safely say, been enumerated. </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">These, then, are qualities, and the things that take their name from them as derivatives, or </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">are in some other way dependent on them, are said to be qualified in some </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">specific way. In most, indeed in almost all cases, the name </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">of that which is qualified is derived from that of </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">the quality. Thus the terms 'whiteness', 'grammar', 'justice', give us </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">the adjectives 'white', 'grammatical', 'just', and so on. There are some cases, however, </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">in which, as the quality under consideration has no name, it is impossible that those possessed </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">of it should have a name that is derivative. For instance, the name given to the </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">runner or boxer, who is so called in virtue of an inborn capacity, is not </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">derived from that of any quality; for lob those capacities have no name assigned to them. </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">In this, the inborn capacity is distinct from the science, with reference to which men are called, </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">e.g. boxers or wrestlers. Such a science is classed as a disposition; it has a name, </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">and is called 'boxing' or 'wrestling' as the case may be, and the name given to </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">those disposed in this way is derived from that of the science. Sometimes, even though </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">a name exists for the quality, that which takes its character </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">from the quality has a name that is not a derivative. For instance, </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">the upright man takes his character from the possession of the quality of integrity, but the name given him is not </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">derived from the word 'integrity'. Yet this does not occur often. We may therefore </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">state that those things are said to be possessed of some specific quality which have a name derived from that of the aforesaid </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">quality, or which are in some other way dependent on it. </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">One quality may be the contrary of another; thus justice is the contrary of injustice, </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">whiteness of blackness, and so on. The things, also, which are said to be such and such in virtue </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">of these qualities, may be contrary the one to the other; for that which is unjust is contrary </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">to that which is just, that which is white to that which is black. This, however, </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">is not always the case. Red, yellow, and such </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">colours, though qualities, have no contraries. If one </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">of two contraries is a quality, the other will also be a quality. </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">This will be evident from particular instances, if we apply the names used to denote the other </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">categories; for instance, granted that justice is the contrary of injustice and justice is a </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">quality, injustice will also be a quality: neither quantity, nor relation, </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">nor place, nor indeed any other category but </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">that of quality, will be applicable properly to injustice. </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">So it is with all other contraries falling under the category </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">of quality. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">Qualities admit of variation of degree. </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">Whiteness is predicated of one thing in a greater or less degree than of another. </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">This is also the case with reference to justice. Moreover, one and the same thing may exhibit </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">a quality in a greater degree than it did before: if a thing is white, it may become whiter. Though </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">this is generally the case, there are exceptions. For if we should say that justice </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">admitted of variation of degree, difficulties might ensue, and this is true with regard </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">to all those qualities which are dispositions. There are some, indeed, who dispute the </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">possibility of variation here. They maintain that justice and health cannot very </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">well admit of variation of degree themselves, but that people </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">vary in the degree in which they possess these qualities, and that </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="11" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">this is the case with grammatical learning and all those qualities which </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">are classed as dispositions. However that may be, it is an incontrovertible fact that the things which in virtue of </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">these qualities are said to be what they are vary in the degree in which they possess them; for </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">one man is said to be better versed in grammar, or </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">more healthy or just, than another, and so on. The qualities expressed by </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">the terms 'triangular' and 'quadrangular' do not appear to admit of variation of degree, nor indeed do </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">any that have to do with figure. For those things to which the definition of </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">the triangle or circle is applicable are all equally triangular or circular. Those, on the </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">other hand, to which the same definition is not applicable, cannot be said to differ </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">from one another in degree; the square is no more a </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">circle than the rectangle, for to neither is the definition of the </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">circle appropriate. In short, if the definition of the term </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">proposed is not applicable to both objects, they cannot be compared. </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">Thus it is not all qualities which admit of variation of degree. </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">Whereas none of the characteristics I have mentioned are peculiar to quality, the fact that likeness and </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">unlikeness can be predicated with reference to quality only, gives to that category its distinctive feature. One </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">thing is like another only with reference to that in virtue of which it is such </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">and such; thus this forms the peculiar </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">mark of quality. </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">We must not be disturbed because it may be argued </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">that, though proposing to discuss the category of quality, we have included </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">in it many relative terms. We did say that habits and dispositions </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">were relative. In practically all such cases the </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">genus is relative, the individual not. Thus knowledge, </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">as a genus, is explained by reference to something else, for we </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">mean a knowledge of something. But particular branches of knowledge are not </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">thus explained. The knowledge of grammar is not relative to anything external, </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">nor is the knowledge of music, but these, if relative at </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">all, are relative only in virtue of their genera; thus grammar </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">is said be the knowledge of something, not the grammar of something; </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">similarly music is the knowledge of something, not the music of something. </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">Thus individual branches of knowledge are not relative. And it is because we possess these individual branches of </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">knowledge that we are said to be such and such. It is these that we actually possess: we </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">are called experts because we possess knowledge in some particular branch. Those </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">particular branches, therefore, of knowledge, in virtue of which we are sometimes </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">said to be such and such, are themselves qualities, and are not relative. </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">Further, if anything should happen to fall within both the category of quality and that of </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">relation, there would be nothing extraordinary in classing it under both these heads. </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">Action and affection both admit of contraries </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">and also of variation of degree. Heating is </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">the contrary of cooling, being heated of being cooled, </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">being glad of being vexed. Thus they admit of contraries. </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">They also admit of variation of degree: for it is possible to </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">heat in a greater or less degree; also to be heated in a </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">greater or less degree. Thus action and affection also </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">admit of variation of degree. </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">So much, then, is stated with regard to these categories. We spoke, moreover, of the category of position when we were </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">dealing with that of relation, and stated that such terms derived their names from those of the corresponding attitudes. As for the rest, </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">time, place, state, since they are easily intelligible, I say no more about them </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">than was said at the beginning, that in the category of state are included </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">such states as 'shod', 'armed', in that of place 'in the Lyceum' and so on, </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">as was explained before. The proposed categories have, then, been adequately dealt </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">with. We must next explain the various senses in which the term 'opposite' is used. </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">Things are said to be opposed in four senses: (i) as </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">correlatives to one another, (ii) as contraries to one another, (iii) as privatives </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">to positives, (iv) as affirmatives to negatives. Let me sketch my meaning in </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">outline. An instance of the use of the word 'opposite' with reference to correlatives is </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">afforded by the expressions 'double' and 'half'; with reference to contraries by 'bad' and </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">'good'. Opposites in the sense of 'privatives' and 'positives' are' blindness' and 'sight'; in </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">the sense of affirmatives and negatives, the propositions 'he sits', 'he does not sit'. </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">(i) Pairs of opposites which fall under the category of relation are explained by a reference of </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">the one to the other, the reference being indicated by the preposition 'of' or by some other preposition. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">Thus, double is a relative term, for that which is double is explained as the </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">double of something. Knowledge, again, is the opposite </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">of the thing known, in the </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">same sense; and the thing known also is explained </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">by its relation to its opposite, knowledge. For the thing known is explained as </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">that which is known by something, that is, by knowledge. </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">Such things, then, as are opposite the one to the other in the sense of </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">being correlatives are explained by a reference of the one to the other. (ii) </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">Pairs of opposites which are contraries are not in any way </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">interdependent, but are contrary the one to the other. The good is not spoken </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">of as the good of the had, but as the contrary of the bad, nor is white spoken of as </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">the white of the black, but as the contrary of the black. These two types of </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">opposition are therefore distinct. Those contraries which are such that the subjects </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="12" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">in which they are naturally present, or of which they are predicated, must </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">necessarily contain either the one or the other of them, have no intermediate, but </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">those in the case of which no such necessity obtains, always have </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">an intermediate. Thus disease and health are naturally present in the body of </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">an animal, and it is necessary that either the one or the other should be </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">present in the body of an animal. Odd and even, again, are predicated </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">of number, and it is necessary that the one or </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">the other should be present in numbers. Now there is no </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">intermediate between the terms of either of these two pairs. </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">On the other hand, in those contraries with regard to which no such necessity obtains, we </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">find an intermediate. Blackness and whiteness are naturally present in the body, but it is not necessary </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">that either the one or the other should be present in the body, inasmuch as it is </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">not true to say that everybody must be white or black. Badness and goodness, again, </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">are predicated of man, and of many other things, but it is not </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">necessary that either the one quality or the other should be present </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">in that of which they are predicated: it is not true to say that everything that may be good or bad </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">must be either good or bad. These pairs of contraries have intermediates: the intermediates between white </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">and black are grey, sallow, and all the other colours that come </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">between; the intermediate between good and bad is that which is neither the one </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">nor the other. Some intermediate qualities have names, such as grey and sallow and </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">all the other colours that come between white and black; in other </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">cases, however, it is not easy to name the intermediate, but we </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">must define it as that which is not either extreme, as in </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">the case of that which is neither good nor bad, neither just </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">nor unjust. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">(iii) 'privatives' and 'Positives' have reference to the same subject. Thus, </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">sight and blindness have reference to the eye. It is a universal rule that </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">each of a pair of opposites of this type has reference to that to which the particular </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">'positive' is natural. We say that that is capable of some particular faculty or possession has suffered privation when </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">the faculty or possession in question is in no way present in that in which, and at the </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">time at which, it should naturally be present. We do not call that toothless which has not </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">teeth, or that blind which has not sight, but rather that which has not teeth or sight </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">at the time when by nature it should. For there are some creatures which from birth </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">are without sight, or without teeth, but these are not called toothless or blind. </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">To be without some faculty or to possess it is not the same as the corresponding 'privative' </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">or 'positive'. 'Sight' is a 'positive', 'blindness' a 'privative', but 'to possess </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">sight' is not equivalent to 'sight', 'to be blind' is not </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">equivalent to 'blindness'. Blindness is a 'privative', to be blind is to be in </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">a state of privation, but is not a 'privative'. Moreover, if 'blindness' </div>
            <div n="40" type="l">were equivalent to 'being blind', both would be predicated of </div>
            <div n="41" type="l">the same subject; but though a man is said to be blind, he </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">is by no means said to be blindness. To be in a state of 'possession' </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">is, it appears, the opposite of being in a state of 'privation', just as 'positives' and 'privatives' themselves </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">are opposite. There is the same type of antithesis in both cases; for </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">just as blindness is opposed to sight, so is being </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">blind opposed to having sight. That which is affirmed or denied </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">is not itself affirmation or denial. By 'affirmation' we </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">mean an affirmative proposition, by 'denial' a negative. Now, those facts </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">which form the matter of the affirmation or denial are </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">not propositions; yet these two are said to be opposed in the same sense as the affirmation and denial, for in </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">this case also the type of antithesis is the same. For as the affirmation is opposed to the denial, as in the </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">two propositions 'he sits', 'he does not sit', so also the fact which constitutes </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">the matter of the proposition in one case is opposed to </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">that in the other, his sitting, that is to say, to </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">his not sitting. It is evident that 'positives' and 'privatives' are not opposed each to each </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">in the same sense as relatives. The one is not explained by reference </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">to the other; sight is not sight of blindness, nor is any other </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">preposition used to indicate the relation. Similarly blindness is </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">not said to be blindness of </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">sight, but rather, privation of sight. Relatives, </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">moreover, reciprocate; if blindness, therefore, were a relative, there would </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">be a reciprocity of relation between it and that with which </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">it was correlative. But this is not the case. Sight is not called </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">the sight of blindness. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">That those terms which fall under the heads of 'positives' and 'privatives' are not opposed </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">each to each as contraries, either, is plain from the following facts: Of a pair of </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">contraries such that they have no intermediate, one or the other must needs be </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">present in the subject in which they naturally subsist, or of which they are predicated; </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">for it is those, as we proved,' in the case of which this </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">necessity obtains, that have no intermediate. Moreover, we cited health and disease, odd and </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">even, as instances. But those contraries which have an intermediate are not subject </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">to any such necessity. It is not necessary that every substance, receptive of </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">such qualities, should be either black or white, cold or hot, for something intermediate between </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">these contraries may very well be present in the subject. We proved, moreover, that </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">those contraries have an intermediate in the case of which the said necessity does not obtain. Yet </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">when one of the two contraries is a constitutive property of the subject, as it is </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">a constitutive property of fire to be hot, of snow to be white, it is </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">necessary determinately that one of the two contraries, not one or the other, should </div>
            <div n="40" type="l">be present in the subject; for fire cannot be </div>
            <div n="41" type="l">cold, or snow black. Thus, it is not the case here that one of </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="13" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">the two must needs be present in every subject receptive of these qualities, but only in that subject of which the </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">one forms a constitutive property. Moreover, in such cases it is one member of the pair determinately, and not either the one </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">or the other, which must be present. In the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', on the other </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">hand, neither of the aforesaid statements holds good. For it is not necessary that a subject receptive </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">of the qualities should always have either the one or the other; that which has not </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">yet advanced to the state when sight is natural is not said either to be blind or to see. Thus </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">'positives' and 'privatives' do not belong to that class of contraries which consists of those which have no intermediate. the </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">other hand, they do not belong either to that class which consists of contraries which have an intermediate. For under certain conditions it is necessary that either the </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">one or the other should form part of the constitution of every appropriate subject. For when a thing has </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">reached the stage when it is by nature capable of sight, it will be said either to see or to be </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">blind, and that in an indeterminate sense, signifying that the capacity may be either present or absent; for it is not necessary </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">either that it should see or that it should be blind, but that it should be either in the one </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">state or in the other. Yet in the case of those contraries which have an intermediate we found that it was never necessary </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">that either the one or the other should be present in every appropriate subject, but only that in certain subjects one </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">of the pair should be present, and that in a determinate sense. It is, therefore, plain that 'positives' </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">and 'privatives' are not opposed each to each in either of the senses </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">in which contraries are opposed. Again, in the case of contraries, it is possible that there </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">should be changes from either into the other, while the subject retains its identity, unless indeed </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">one of the contraries is a constitutive property of that subject, as heat is of fire. For </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">it is possible that that that which is healthy should become diseased, </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">that which is white, black, that which is cold, hot, that which </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">is good, bad, that which is bad, good. The bad man, if </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">he is being brought into a better way of life and thought, </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">may make some advance, however slight, and if he should once improve, even </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">ever so little, it is plain that he might change completely, or at any rate </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">make very great progress; for a man becomes more and more easily moved to virtue, however small </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">the improvement was at first. It is, therefore, natural to suppose that he will make yet greater </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">progress than he has made in the past; and as this process goes on, it </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">will change him completely and establish him in the contrary state, provided he is not hindered </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">by lack of time. In the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">however, change in both directions is impossible. There may be </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">a change from possession to privation, but </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">not from privation to possession. The man who has become blind does not </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">regain his sight; the man who has become bald does not regain his hair; the man who has lost his </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">teeth does not grow his grow a new set. </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">(iv) Statements opposed as affirmation and negation </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">belong manifestly to a class which is distinct, </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">for in this case, and in this case only, it is necessary for the one opposite </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">to be true and the other false. Neither in the case of contraries, nor in </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">the case of correlatives, nor in the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', is it </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">necessary for one to be true and the other false. Health </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">and disease are contraries: neither of them is true </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">or false. 'Double' and 'half' are opposed to each </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">other as correlatives: neither of them is true or </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">false. The case is the same, of course, with regard to 'positives' and 'privatives' such as </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">'sight' and 'blindness'. In short, where there is no sort of combination </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">of words, truth and falsity have no place, and all the opposites </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">we have mentioned so far consist of simple words. At the same time, when </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">the words which enter into opposed statements are contraries, these, more than any other set of </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">opposites, would seem to claim this characteristic. 'Socrates is ill' is the contrary of </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">'Socrates is well', but not even of such composite expressions is it true to say that </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">one of the pair must always be true and the other false. For if Socrates </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">exists, one will be true and the other false, but if he does not </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">exist, both will be false; for neither 'Socrates is ill' nor 'Socrates </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">is well' is true, if Socrates does not exist at all. </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">In the case of 'positives' and 'privatives', if the subject does not exist at all, neither proposition is true, </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">but even if the subject exists, it is not always the fact that one is true and the other false. </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">For 'Socrates has sight' is the opposite of 'Socrates is blind' in </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">the sense of the word 'opposite' which applies to possession and </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">privation. Now if Socrates exists, it is not necessary that one </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">should be true and the other false, for when he is not </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">yet able to acquire the power of vision, both are false, as </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">also if Socrates is altogether non-existent. But in the case </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">of affirmation and negation, whether the subject exists or not, </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">one is always false and the other true. For manifestly, if </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">Socrates exists, one of the two propositions 'Socrates is ill', </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">'Socrates is not ill', is true, and the other false. </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">This is likewise the case if he does not exist; for if he does not exist, to say that he is ill is false, to say that he is not </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">ill is true. Thus it is in the case of those opposites only, which are opposite in the sense in which the </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">term is used with reference to affirmation and negation, that the rule holds good, that one of the pair must </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">be true and the other false. </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">That the contrary of a good is an evil </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">is shown by induction: the contrary of health is disease, </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="14" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">of courage, cowardice, and so on. But the contrary of an </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">evil is sometimes a good, sometimes an evil. For defect, which is </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">an evil, has excess for its contrary, this also being an evil, and the mean, which is </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">a good, is equally the contrary of the one and of the other. It is only in </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">a few cases, however, that we see instances of this: in most, the contrary </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">of an evil is a good. In the case of contraries, it is not always necessary </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">that if one exists the other should also exist: for if all become healthy there </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">will be health and no disease, and again, if everything turns </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">white, there will be white, but no black. Again, since the fact </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">that Socrates is ill is the contrary of the fact that Socrates is well, and </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">two contrary conditions cannot both obtain in one and the same individual at the </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">same time, both these contraries could not exist at once: for if that Socrates was well </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">was a fact, then that Socrates was ill could not possibly be one. </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">It is plain that contrary attributes must needs be present in subjects which belong </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">to the same species or genus. Disease and health require as their subject the body of </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">an animal; white and black require a body, without further qualification; justice and injustice require as </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">their subject the human soul. Moreover, it is necessary that pairs of contraries should in all cases </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">either belong to the same genus or belong to contrary genera or be themselves genera. White </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">and black belong to the same genus, </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">colour; justice and injustice, to contrary genera, virtue </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">and vice; while good and evil do not belong </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">to genera, but are themselves actual genera, with terms </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">under them. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">There are four senses in which one thing can be said to be 'prior' to another. Primarily and </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">most properly the term has reference to time: in this sense the </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">word is used to indicate that one thing is older or more ancient than another, </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">for the expressions 'older' and 'more ancient' imply greater length of time. Secondly, one </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">thing is said to be 'prior' to another when the sequence of </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">their being cannot be reversed. In this sense 'one' is 'prior' to 'two'. </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">For if 'two' exists, it follows directly that 'one' must exist, but if 'one' exists, it </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">does not follow necessarily that 'two' exists: thus the sequence subsisting cannot be reversed. It is </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">agreed, then, that when the sequence of two things cannot be reversed, then that one on </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">which the other depends is called 'prior' to that other. In the third place, the term 'prior' </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">is used with reference to any order, as in the case of science and </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">of oratory. For in sciences which use demonstration there is that which is </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">prior and that which is posterior in order; in geometry, the elements </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">are prior to the propositions; in reading and writing, the letters of </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">the alphabet are prior to the syllables. Similarly, in the case </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">of speeches, the exordium is prior in order to the narrative. Besides </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">these senses of the word, there is a fourth. That which is better and more honourable </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">is said to have a natural priority. In common parlance men speak </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">of those whom they honour and love as </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">'coming first' with them. This sense of the word is </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">perhaps the most far-fetched. </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">Such, then, are the different senses in which the term 'prior' </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">is used. Yet it would seem that besides those </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">mentioned there is yet another. For in those things, the being of each of which </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">implies that of the other, that which is in any way the cause may reasonably be </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">said to be by nature 'prior' to the effect. It is plain that there are instances </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">of this. The fact of the being of a man carries with it the </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">truth of the proposition that he is, and the implication is reciprocal: for </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">if a man is, the proposition wherein we allege that he </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">is true, and conversely, if the proposition wherein we allege </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">that he is true, then he is. The true proposition, however, is </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">in no way the cause of the being of the man, but the fact of </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">the man's being does seem somehow to be the cause of the truth of the proposition, </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">for the truth or falsity of the proposition depends on the fact of the </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">man's being or not being. Thus the word 'prior' may be used </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">in five senses. </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">The term 'simultaneous' is primarily and most appropriately applied to those things the genesis of the one </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">of which is simultaneous with that of the other; for in such cases neither is prior </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">or posterior to the other. Such things are said to be simultaneous in point of time. </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">Those things, again, are 'simultaneous' in point of nature, the being </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">of each of which involves that of the other, while at </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">the same time neither is the cause of the other's being. This is the case with regard </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">to the double and the half, for these are reciprocally dependent, since, if there is a double, there is also a </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">half, and if there is a half, there is also a double, while at the same time neither is the cause of </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">the being of the other. Again, those species which are distinguished one from another and opposed one to another within </div>
            <div n="34" type="l">the same genus are said to be 'simultaneous' in nature. I mean those species which are distinguished </div>
            <div n="35" type="l">each from each by one and the same method of division. Thus the 'winged' species is simultaneous </div>
            <div n="36" type="l">with the 'terrestrial' and the 'water' species. These are distinguished within the same genus, </div>
            <div n="37" type="l">and are opposed each to each, for the genus 'animal' has the 'winged', the </div>
            <div n="38" type="l">'terrestrial', and the 'water' species, and no one of these is </div>
            <div n="39" type="l">prior or posterior to another; on the contrary, all such things appear </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div n="15" type="p">
         <div n="a" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">to be 'simultaneous' in nature. Each of these also, the terrestrial, </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">the winged, and the water species, can be divided again </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">into subspecies. Those species, then, also will be 'simultaneous' point of nature, which, belonging to the same genus, </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">are distinguished each from each by one and the same method of differentiation. But genera are </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">prior to species, for the sequence of their being </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">cannot be reversed. If there is the species 'water-animal', there will be the genus 'animal', but granted the being of the genus 'animal', </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">it does not follow necessarily that there will be the species 'water-animal'. Those things, therefore, are said to be 'simultaneous' </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">in nature, the being of each of which involves that of the other, while at the same </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">time neither is in any way the cause of the other's being; those species, also, which are distinguished </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">each from each and opposed within the same genus. Those things, moreover, are 'simultaneous' in the unqualified sense of the word which </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">come into being at the same time. </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">There are six sorts of movement: generation, destruction, increase, </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">diminution, alteration, and change of place. It is evident in all </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">but one case that all these sorts of movement are distinct each from each. Generation is </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">distinct from destruction, increase and change of place </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">from diminution, and so on. But in the case of </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">alteration it may be argued that the process necessarily implies one or other </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">of the other five sorts of motion. This is not true, for </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">we may say that all affections, or nearly all, produce in us </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">an alteration which is distinct from all other sorts of motion, </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">for that which is affected need not suffer either increase </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">or diminution or any of the other sorts of motion. </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">Thus alteration is a distinct sort of motion; for, if it </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">were not, the thing altered would not only be altered, but would forthwith necessarily suffer increase or </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">diminution or some one of the other sorts of motion in addition; which as a matter of fact is not the case. </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">Similarly that which was undergoing the process of increase or was subject to some other sort of motion would, if alteration were not </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">a distinct form of motion, necessarily be subject to alteration also. But there are some things which undergo increase </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">but yet not alteration. The square, for instance, if a gnomon is </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">applied to it, undergoes increase but not alteration, and so it </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">is with all other figures of this sort. Alteration and increase, </div>
            <div n="33" type="l">therefore, are distinct. </div>
         </div>
         <div n="b" type="c">
            <div n="1" type="l">Speaking generally, rest is the contrary of motion. But the different </div>
            <div n="2" type="l">forms of motion have their own contraries in other forms; thus destruction is the contrary of generation, diminution of increase, </div>
            <div n="3" type="l">rest in a place, of change of place. As for this </div>
            <div n="4" type="l">last, change in the reverse direction would seem to be most truly </div>
            <div n="5" type="l">its contrary; thus motion upwards is the contrary of motion downwards and </div>
            <div n="6" type="l">vice versa. In the case of that sort of motion which yet </div>
            <div n="7" type="l">remains, of those that have been enumerated, it is not easy to </div>
            <div n="8" type="l">state what is its contrary. It appears to have no contrary, unless </div>
            <div n="9" type="l">one should define the contrary here also either as 'rest in its quality' or </div>
            <div n="10" type="l">as 'change in the direction of the contrary quality', just as </div>
            <div n="11" type="l">we defined the contrary of change of place either as rest in </div>
            <div n="12" type="l">a place or as change in the reverse direction. For a thing is </div>
            <div n="13" type="l">altered when change of quality takes place; therefore either rest in its quality or change in </div>
            <div n="14" type="l">the direction of the contrary may be called the contrary of this qualitative form of motion. In this </div>
            <div n="15" type="l">way becoming white is the contrary of becoming black; there is alteration in the contrary direction, </div>
            <div n="16" type="l">since a change of a qualitative nature takes place. </div>
            <div n="17" type="l">The term 'to have' is used in various senses. In </div>
            <div n="18" type="l">the first place it is used with reference to habit or disposition or any other quality, </div>
            <div n="19" type="l">for we are said to 'have' a piece of knowledge or a virtue. Then, again, it has </div>
            <div n="20" type="l">reference to quantity, as, for instance, in the case of a man's height; for he is </div>
            <div n="21" type="l">said to 'have' a height of three or four cubits. It is used, moreover, with regard to apparel, a </div>
            <div n="22" type="l">man being said to 'have' a coat or tunic; or in respect of something which we have on a part of ourselves, as </div>
            <div n="23" type="l">a ring on the hand: or in respect of something which is a part of us, as hand or foot. The term refers </div>
            <div n="24" type="l">also to content, as in the case of a vessel and wheat, or of a </div>
            <div n="25" type="l">jar and wine; a jar is said to 'have' wine, and a corn-measure wheat. </div>
            <div n="26" type="l">The expression in such cases has reference to content. it refers to that which has been acquired; </div>
            <div n="27" type="l">we are said to 'have' a house or a field. A man is also </div>
            <div n="28" type="l">said to 'have' a wife, and a wife a husband, and this appears to be </div>
            <div n="29" type="l">the most remote meaning of the term, for by the use of it we </div>
            <div n="30" type="l">mean simply that the husband lives with the wife. Other senses of the </div>
            <div n="31" type="l">word might perhaps be found, but the most ordinary ones </div>
            <div n="32" type="l">have all been enumerated. </div>
         </div>
      </div>
   </body>
</TAN-T>
